<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermo[n] made by Iohn Chrisostome patriarche of Constantinople, of pacience, of ye end of ye world, and of ye last iudgeme[n]t. Whereunto is added an other homelie made by John Brentius of the vertue of Christes resurrectio[n] tra[n]slated into Englishe by Thomas Sa[m]pson</title>
            <title>De patientia et de consumatione huius sæculi, de secundo adventu. English</title>
            <author>John Chrysostom, Saint, d. 407.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1550</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04511</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14638</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103723</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839468</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839468</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3894</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04511)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3894)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 55:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermo[n] made by Iohn Chrisostome patriarche of Constantinople, of pacience, of ye end of ye world, and of ye last iudgeme[n]t. Whereunto is added an other homelie made by John Brentius of the vertue of Christes resurrectio[n] tra[n]slated into Englishe by Thomas Sa[m]pson</title>
                  <title>De patientia et de consumatione huius sæculi, de secundo adventu. English</title>
                  <author>John Chrysostom, Saint, d. 407.</author>
                  <author>Brenz, Johannes, 1499-1570. Homelye of the resurrection of Christe. aut</author>
                  <author>Sampson, Thomas, 1517?-1589.</author>
                  <author>Castellion, Sébastien, 1515-1563.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[80] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In S. Johns strete by Nicolas Hyll, for John Shefelde],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. do. 1550.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of "De patientia et de consumatione huius sæculi, de secundo adventu", which was translated from Greek to Latin by John Theophilus, i.e. Sébastien Castellion.--Folger Shakespeare Library Catalogue.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, Early Christian --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3894:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3894:1"/>
            <p>A ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made by Iohn Chriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome patriarche of Conſtantinople, of paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Wherunto is added an other Homelie made by Iohn Brentius of the vertue of Chriſtes re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated into Engliſhe by Thomas Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ⸪ Anno. do. 1550.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3894:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3894:2"/>
            <head>¶Grace peace and mercy from God our father, and the Lorde Ieſus our Sauiour, be with the beloued Reader in the Lorde.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hree thynges there are, whiche Chriſt our ſauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oure taught con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyng the daye of iudgemente: Fyrſte to what ioyes the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſhalbe receyued: Secondly what horryble paynes the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faythfull and wycked ſhal abid: Thyrdely howe ſodayne the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng of that daye ſhall be. And of this ſodayne commyng he ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth in the goſpelles muche and
<pb facs="tcp:3894:3"/>
large mencion, and compareth it to the comming of the floude, to the burnyng of Sodo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to a ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenyng whiche (as it were in the twi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ckli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of an eie) goeth from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eaſt vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weſt, to a thefe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth on a mannes houſe in the nyght tyme, and ſayth he, <hi>In ſuch an houre as ye thynke not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.</note> 
               <hi>VVill the ſonne of manne come,</hi> thus not ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng when the day ſhall be, he dothe teache no more but that ſodaynely it wyll come. Thys thyng he dyd ſo diligently teach, forſeing that men wolde be ſlug<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gardes &amp; idle, neither watching for the daye, nor yet preparinge them ſelues to the iudgemente, therfore he ſtil cried <hi>VVatche VVat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che,</hi> both ſignifing that he wold not haue vs taken vnwares, and alſo teachyng vs that we ſhould be faythful ſeruauntes in our vo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cacyon,
<pb facs="tcp:3894:3"/>
miniſtring righteouſnes towardes our brethren, and not become tirauntes and bellye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gods, as they do whiche thynke not at al of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng: that we myght alſo haue oyle in our lam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes and oure lampes burnynge, ſuche fruites of faithe that men may ſe our good workes &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryfie the father whiche is in hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen, and ſo meete the Lorde our bridegrome in the ayre, to enter with him into the kyngdome of heauen. This was one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of Chriſtes teaching concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng this matier. Nowe a man wolde thinke, that if there hadde neuer bene any more ſpoken of this thynge, this warning &amp; tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chynge of Chriſt had been ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to haue made all men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs, &amp; to make vs alſo moſte chiefely whiche are in the latter
<pb facs="tcp:3894:4"/>
endes of the world, circumſpect, watchinge and prepared accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyngly to receyue the Lorde.</p>
            <p>But neyther his teachynge, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſame doctrine taught by his Apoſtles, whiche we reade and heare euery daye, neyther y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wryting of the olde fathers fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> age to age of this mater, neither the preching and writing in this our tyme, &amp; that more is though that all the ſygnes and tokens whiche ſhoulde go before that daye are al ready come and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, yet can none of all theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges make vs to watche, and pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pare our ſelues for that daye, ſo greate is our ſynnefull ſecuritie. What I praye you wyll be the ende of this our ſecure and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les lyfe and ſynnynge? Forſothe this, that it ſhal be rewarded w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the payne due for the contempte
<pb facs="tcp:3894:4"/>
of God, that our partes muſt be with the tirannous and fleſſhlye ſeruaunt, and with the ſloggiſhe careles &amp; folyſhe virgins, which is in that vtter darkenes where we ſhall haue no other chere but wepyng and gnaſhyng of teeth. This is an vndoubted truth.</p>
            <p>The mouthe of the Lorde hath ſpoken it. Let all them therfore that do deſyre to be partakers of the kyngdome of God, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them ſelues, forſake ſynne, labour for fayth, and ſet on fyre their lampes gyuyng forthe the frutes of faith, and conſyder the day of the Lord to be nowe nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer at hande then euer it was, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhal al ariſe, both good, and bad. Watche therfore. The which that thou maieſt be occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better to do, I gyue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the (good Reader) tranſlated
<pb facs="tcp:3894:5"/>
into Engliſhe theſe two litle ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mons, one of Chriſoſtome, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che doth emongeſt manye other notable leſſons full erneſtly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monyſhe thee of that daye: The other of Iohn Brentius, whych teacheth the vertue and effect of Chriſtes reſurrection. Be thou therfore (good Reader) by the reading of theſe once again war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned to prepare thy ſelf vnto that day, &amp; ſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> henceforth now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue thy ſelf, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> when the Lorde ſhal come y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> maiſt be founde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable, &amp; ſo able to ſtadde in his ſight, that thou maieſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with him into glory: Which grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto vs all, that Lorde, that ſhal iudge vs al, to whom be glory for euer.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:3894:5"/>
            <head>¶A ſermon of Iohn Chriſoſtome, patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arche of Conſtantynople, of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende of this world: of the ſeconde commynge of the Lord: &amp; of the euerlaſting ioyes of the iuſte, and paines of the euill. Tranſlated oute of greke into latin by Iohn Theophilus, and oute of Latin into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyſhe by T.S.</head>
            <p>THe life of the iuſt, trulye, is excellent. But howe doeth it floriſhe, but by pacience? Loue it, my brother, as the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth. For the Pſalme-writer doth admonyſhe the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note> 
               <hi>Hope thou in the Lorde and kepe
<pb facs="tcp:3894:6"/>
his VVaye.</hi> And Paul to the ende that thou mighteſt kepe this ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue ſayth:<note place="margin">Rom. v.</note> 
               <hi>Tribulacion bringeth pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience.</hi> The whiche if thou exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſe, thou ſhalt fynd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpryng of all goodneſſe, whyche is hope, <hi>and hope maketh not aſhamed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note> 
               <hi>Holde the ſtyll in the Lorde, and abyde pacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently upon him.</hi> For euen therby ſhalt thou verely fynde a thynge that is not to be highly eſtemed. <hi>And he ſhal geue the thy hertes deſire.</hi> What is more bleſſed then this man, which, as his owne, hathe the welwyllynge eares, of ſo greate a kynge? Who deſyreth not to haue the Iudge to gyue eare, and to ſhewe him fauoure? My brother, thou arte the work ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vertue. Chriſt hath hyred the into his vyneyard. Whyles y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt tyme worke goodnes. Giue care to Paule whyche ſayeth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3894:6"/>
               <hi>VVatſoeuer a man ſovveth, that ſhall he reape</hi> Sowe in the ſpirite,<note place="margin">Galat. vi.</note> that thou mayeſt reape euerlaſtynge lyfe. For he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſoweth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſſhe ſhall of the fleſhe reape corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. And herken vnto an other admoniſher which ſaith.<note place="margin">Oſe x.</note> 
               <hi>SoVVe unto the righteouſneſſe, and reape the fruites of VVeldoyng.</hi> Be not wery of thy labour: for there is hope of harueſt, and time of gatheri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. For wher as appoynted games are, there are rewardes: where battailes, there are honours got<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: where fight, there is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crown of vyctorie. Haue an eye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe thynges, and harneſſe thy ſelfe vnto pacyence. Let hym alwayes ſownde in thyne eares, whiche crieth with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes. <hi>Be ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. xxvi.</note> 
               <hi>let thine hert be of good comfort, and VVayte thou ſtyll for the Lorde.</hi> Prepare thy workes: huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonde
<pb facs="tcp:3894:7"/>
thy feelde. Thy lyfe is the feelde. Take a good matthooke, I meane the olde and newe te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament: make an hedge aboute thy grounde with thornes, that is, with doctryne, prayer, and faſtynge. If y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haue thys hedge, the beaſte that is the Deuyl ſhal not breake into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. Till thy ſoule as a good vineyarde. And as the keapers of vyneyardes do clap their handes, and crye out wyth their voyce, and with ſuche noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes they dryue away ſuch as do pryuily lurcke to ſpoyle them, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo do y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> crye in prayer, make noyſe with ſingyng of pſalmes, and thou ſhalt dryue awaye the euyll beſt, the foxe, that is to ſay the deuyll. Of the whiche beſte the ſcripture ſpeaketh. <hi>Get you the foxes. &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cantic. 2.</note> Take good heede al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes of the enemye. If he doth
<pb facs="tcp:3894:7"/>
ſhote at thy herte with vnlawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful luſt, if he with his darte doth caſt his fylthye thoughtes in to thy mynde, caſte forthe agaynſte him the ſhelde of fayth,<note place="margin">Epheſ. vi.</note> turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt hym the helmet of hope, take to thee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſword of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite, whiche is the word of God. And when thou art ſo harneſſed abid thine enemye. Be not faynte her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted in the batell. But in all poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes be ſober, and ſay,<note place="margin">ii. Cor. ii.</note> 
               <hi>His though<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes are not VnknoVVen to us.</hi> Be ioy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full alwayes: as it is wrytten. <hi>Let your ſoftnes be knoVVen unto all men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Philip. 4.</note> Let the feare of God lygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in thy hert. Be not a coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſouldiour, be not fearfull, &amp; a ſlowe workma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, fle not from the crown of victorie. Life is ſhort, but the iudgement is longe. Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng vnto this, ſpeake vnto thin owne herte and ſay with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:3894:8"/>
prophet.<note place="margin">Pſal. xxvi.</note> 
               <hi>Be ſtronge, and let thy hert be of good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, &amp; VVaite thou ſtyll for the Lorde.</hi>
               <note place="margin">i. Reg. xvii.</note> Folowe Dauid and with one caſt of a ſtone ouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>throw thyne enemye. The Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles are aboute the, as the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders of thy lyfe:<note place="margin">i. Cor. iiii.</note> 
               <hi>Vue are made (ſayeth he) a gaſynge ſtocke, to the VVorld, and to the Aungelles, and to men.</hi> If they ſhall ſe that thou o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercommeſt, they ſhall reioyce in thy good worke, but if they ſhal ſe the to be ouercome, they ſhall departfull ſad, nether ſhall they be able to loke vpon the, but the deuils ſhal mocke the. Therfore take for thy ſworde the feare of of God. For the feare of God is a two edged ſworde, cuttyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye all euyll luſtes. Take vnto the therefore alwayes the feare of God.<note place="margin">Of the laſt daye</note> And remembre continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally that ſame laſt daye, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
<pb facs="tcp:3894:8"/>
heauens ſhalbe deſtroyed wyth fire, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> elementes ſhall melte away with heate,<note place="margin">ii. Pete. iii.</note> but the earthe and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workes that are in it ſhall be burnt vp. When the ſterres ſhall fall downe as leaues. The Sunne &amp; Moone ſhall be made darke,<note place="margin">Luke. xxi. Mat. 24.</note> and ſhall not gyue their lyght. When the Sonne of God ſhalbe openly ſhewed, and ſhall come down from the heauen vp on the earth, &amp; the powers of the heauens ſhall be moued. When Aungelles ſhall paſſe hyther and thyther, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſowndes of the trom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pettes ſhall come, fire ſhal burne before him, and runnyng vp and downe ſhall burne vp the whole worlde. In the compaſſe aboute hym ſhall be a myghtye tempeſt. There ſhalbe earthquakes, and lyghtninges, ſuch as neuer were before, nether yet are vnto thys
<pb facs="tcp:3894:9"/>
daye. In ſo muche that the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye powers of heauen ſhall be ſmytten wyth great feare. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, my brother, what manner parſones oughte we to be then? What feare,<note place="margin">Exod. xix.</note> what deadly dread ſhall come vpon vs? Remembre howe that the Iſraelites coulde not in the wylderneſſe abyde the clowde and darckneſſe, and the voyce of GOD ſpeakynge out of the myddeſt of the fire, but cauſed that he ſhulde not ſpeake vnto theym, neyther were they able to abyde hym, when he yet hydde moche of his maieſty, yea though y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he neither came down to them in anger, nor yet ſpake angrily vnto them. Gyue eare therfore my brother, yf they wer not able to abyde his commyng whiche comforted theym, when as neyther the heauens burning
<pb facs="tcp:3894:9"/>
were deſtroyed, neither the erth nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thynges that are in it were burned vp, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there was none that blewe anye ſuche trompet, as that trompet ſhal ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſhal raiſe vp al them that haue ſleapte ſithens the begynnynge of the world, neither did the fire burne the world, neither yet hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pened there the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any of thoſe fear full thinges whiche ſhall come.</p>
            <p>What ſhall we do, when he ſhal come downe with ſuche anger &amp; wrath as is intollerable, &amp; ſhall ſyt vpon the ſeate of his glorye, and ſhal call before him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole earth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the riſyng of the ſunne to the goyng downe therof: and from all the endes of the earth, that he may iudge his people, &amp; gyue vnto euery one of them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to his workes. Alas what maner parſons ought we
<pb facs="tcp:3894:10"/>
to be, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhal ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpnaked, &amp; vnclothed, to be broughte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeate. Ah, wo is me. Where is then our colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red hipocriſie, &amp; where is then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> might of the fleſhe? where is the beawtye which is bothe diſceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and vnprofitable? where is then the ſwetnes of mans voice? where becommeth then ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les and vnſhamefaſed pratyng? where is the araye of garmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes? where is the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pleaſure of ſynne, which is in dede vncleane and filthie? where are they then whiche drynke theyr wyne with theyr tabours and inſtrumentes of muſyke and do not loke vpon the workes of GOD? where is then the contempt of thoſe men, whiche do nowe lyue wythoute feare? where are then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fine plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſures and nyce tenderneſſe? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:3894:10"/>
al thinges are paſſed away, and are diſſolued euen as the enfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted aire. Where is the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gredy deſyre of monye and ryches, and the vnmercyfulneſſe whiche al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes folowethe it? where is then that cruel pride which doth horribly hate all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſemeth vnto it ſelfe to be ſomewhat?</p>
            <p>Where is then the vnprofytable and vayne glorye of men? where is then myghte, and tyrannye? where then is Kynge? where is Prynce? where is Duke? where then are theſe proude Rulers, whiche by reaſon of theyr riches do contempne God? Then when they ſhal perceiue that this was ſpoken of them. <hi>They meruayled, they were aſtonyed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. xlvii. and .xlviii.</note> 
               <hi>and ſodenlye caſte downe, feare came vpon them, they are troubled, feare toke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> There ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be ſorowes as are the ſorowes
<pb facs="tcp:3894:11"/>
of a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that trauaileth, they ſhalbe torne in peeces w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſpirite. But where is the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiſe? where be their new inuencio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s? Wo, wo to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? They are moued oute of their place, they are caſte downe euen as a droncken man, and all their wiſedome is ſwalowed vp.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">i. Cor. i.</note>
               <hi>Where is the wiſe? Where is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrybe?</hi> where is the raker of treaſure to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether of thys vayne worlde? My brother, wey with thy ſelfe what maner of parſons we ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be when we muſt giue an acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of thoſe thinges whych we haue done, aſwell greate thynges as ſmall. For vntyll ſuche tyme as we haue iuſtly ſatiſfyced y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> iuſte iudgemente, in what condicion ſhall we be? And howe carefull ſhall we be,<note place="margin">The euer laſtyng ioyes of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</note> that we maye fynde fauour before him? But what
<pb facs="tcp:3894:11"/>
maner of ioye ſhal come vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, whiche are ſet a parte vpon the rightha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of God? In what caſe ſhall we be then, when all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of God ſhall ſalute vs? Abra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ham ſhall ſalute the, Iſaac, and Iacob, Moſes, Noe, Iob, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, and all the holy Prophetes, Apoſtles, and Martirs: and all thoſe righteous men which plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed God in the life of their fleſhe: and how many ſhalt thou heare there, &amp; ſhalte maruayle at their lyfe, whom a litle before thou de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſireſt but to ſee? They ſhal there come vnto the, beyng very glad for thy ſaluacion. Howe ſhal we then be inwardly moued? What vnſpekable ioye ſhall y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be, when the kinge in his gracyous good moode ſhall ſaye vnto them that be on his ryght hande.<note place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Come ye children of my father, &amp; poſſeſſe the king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome,
<pb facs="tcp:3894:12"/>
whiche is prepared for you frome the begynnyng of the worlde.</hi> Then ſhalte thou my brother receyue that moſt gloryous kyngdome, and the princely crowne of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye of the hande of the Lorde, &amp; from thence forthe ſhalte thou raigne with Chriſt. Then ſhalte y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> receiue for thine enherytaunce thoſe euerlaſtyng goodes which God hath prepared for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that loue him. Then euer afterward ſhalte thou be without careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; without al feare. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, my brother, what it is to raigne in heuen, for as we ſaid before, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt receyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crowne of glorye at the hand of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, and ſhalt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thenceforth raigne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y with thy ſelfe my brother, what a thynge it is alwayes to beholde the face of God? What a lyght is in it:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Sunne ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:3894:12"/>
be thy day lyght, (as Eſai ſaid) &amp; the lyght of the Moone ſhall neuer ſhine vnto the: but the Lord God ſhalbe thine euerlaſtyng lyght, and thy God ſhall be thy glorye.</hi> Beholde my brother, what maner of ioyes are layed vp for them which feare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, and whiche do kepe hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes.</p>
            <p>Furthermore caſt in thy mind my brother alſo the deſtruction of ſynners.<note place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructyon and the payne of the euyll men.</note> When they ſhall be brought before the dredful iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement ſeate, with howe great baſhfulneſſe ſhal they be amaſed before the iuſt iudge, when they ſhall not haue one worde to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere. Howe ſhall they be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord ſhall ſpeake vnto them in his wrathe, and in his anger ſhal trouble the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſayi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Departe from me ye curſed into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge fire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. xxv.</note> 
               <hi>whiche is prepared for the Deuil and his aungels.</hi> Alas, alas, in
<pb facs="tcp:3894:13"/>
what affliction, and perplexitye ſhall their ſpirites be, when all ſhall maynely crye out? ſayinge. <hi>Let the ſynners be turned into hell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. ix.</note> 
               <hi>and all nacyons whiche do forget GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alas, alas, what a ſorowful ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſhall they ſynge wryngyng their handes and ſorowyng, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhalbe at the poynte to be ledde awaye, that they maye be cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puniſſhed for euer and euer? Alas, alas, what a place is that, where there is wepyng &amp; gnaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhynge of teeth, whiche is called Hell, the whiche place the Deuil him ſelfe doeth horriblye feare? Alas what a fyre is that fire of Hell whiche ſhalbe neuer quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched oute? Alas, what a poyſon worme is that that neuer ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth gnawynge?<note place="margin">Eſay. 66. Ezech. xx. Mark. ix,</note> Alas how gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous are thoſe vtter darkneſſes whiche contynue for euer? Alas
<pb facs="tcp:3894:13"/>
what manner of mynyſters are they whiche are appoynted to haue the ordrynge of the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, whiche lackynge bothe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye, and tender hert, do ſtyl ſpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully vpbrayde and beete? Then they whiche are punyſſhed ſhall crye ſtrongly vnto the Lord, and he ſhal not heare them. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal they knowe that al thynges that were in this lyfe were but vaine thinges, and tranſitorie, and the thynges whiche they thoughte here to be ſwete, they fynde that they are more bitter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any gal or poyſon. Where is then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the fleſhe, which is falſly ſo called? For there is no other pleaſure, but to feare the Lord.<note place="margin">To feare the lorde is true pleaſure.</note> For it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true pleaſure, for this doth in dede fyll the ſoule as w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> luſte and fatnes. Then ſhal they deſpaire of them ſelues, and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3894:14"/>
workes which they haue wrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght. Then ſhal they confeſſe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge. <hi>Iuſt is the iudgement of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Haue we herde theſe thynges, &amp; wolde we not turne from our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill workes? And then it ſhal no thynge auayle them. Alas wo is me, whiche beyng taken w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch ſynnes, as no man hath done the lyke, haue ſynned aboue the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the ſande, and am holden backe of them as if it were with many yron cheynes. I haue no hope that I ſhal loke vp into he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. To whom then ſhall I flee, but vnto the thou mercifull? but vnto the whiche doeſt not reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber wronges?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A prayer.</note>HAue mercy vpon me o God after thy great mercye, and accordynge to the multitude of thy mercyes do away my iniqui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie.
<pb facs="tcp:3894:14"/>
Waſſhe me more from my ſynnes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note> and purge me from my wyckednes: for I knowe myne iniquitie, and my ſynne is euer agaynſte me. Agaynſte the onely haue I ſynned, and I haue done euill in thy ſyght. Vnto the do I flee, for thy great mercy and thy goodnes. I haue prouoked thee, and I do flee vnto thee, euen for thy very gentlenes to be entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. I haue call the awaye, and I flee vnto thee, for thy greate goodneſſe and thy gentleneſſe.</p>
            <p>And I pray vnto thee, beſeching thee, that thou wylte turne thy face from my ſynnes, and put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye all my myſededes. Make in me a cleane herte O God, and renue a ryght ſpirite within me, for thy only names ſake. For I haue nothynge that I ſhulde of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vnto the, not one good work,
<pb facs="tcp:3894:15"/>
no cleane herte, but truſtynge in thy mercies I caſte my ſelfe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:<note place="margin">Chriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom had no good workes to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by.</note> That thou wylt worke, in me repentaunce, ſo that I fal not eaſyly agayne into ſinne, but fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this tyme forth I may ſerue the in holines and ryghteouſnes all the dayes of my lyfe, forthine is the Kyngdome and Empire for euer and euer. So be it.</p>
            <p>I Beſeche thee my brother which lokeſt for theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, that thou ſtudye to be found cleane, and without ſpot, in peace. Yf anye euyll thoughte come vnto the, laye hold on this ſworde: that is to ſay, thinke vp on the feare of GOD, and thou ſhalte cut downe all the power of the enemye. Take vnto the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in ſteade of a trompet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holye ſcriptures: for as the trompette
<pb facs="tcp:3894:15"/>
gathereth together the ſouldy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours euen ſo the holy ſcriptures when they crye vnto vs, they ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther together our thoughtes in the feare of the Lorde. For oure thoughtes are as ſouldyours which do fyght the fielde agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the enemyes of the kynge. And agayne. As the trompet that ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth in the tyme of battayle ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vp the corrage of the yonge men and them that fyght agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the enemyes, euen ſo the holye ſcriptures do ſtyrre vp thy redy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, vnto that whiche is good, &amp; make the manly agaynſt euil af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. Therfore my brother, aſmuche as thou canſte, compell thy ſelfe to be often occupied in them, that they maye gather to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether thy thoughtes, which the enemye doeth ſcater abrode by his wycked inuencions, ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinge
<pb facs="tcp:3894:16"/>
vnto the euyll luſtes: ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther els ſome tymes ſendyng vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on thee ſome troubles: either els nowe and then miniſtryng vnto thee wealth and ſecuritie. Theſe thynges he worketh by his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyce and guyle, to thende that he myght turne man fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God. For ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tymes it chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he can not wynne &amp; ouercome a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through luſtes, then afterwarde he wyll brynge vnto him tempta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cions, to darcken the mynd, that he may afterward fynde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame more apte for his purpoſe, to the ende that he may then ſowe in to it ſuche thinges as he liſteth: and he beginneth ſomtimes to moue man to thynke on this wiſe, and, as it were, to ſweare. That ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens the tyme that I begon to do good, I haue had verye euyll lucke. Let vs therfore do euyll y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3894:16"/>
good may come theron. Then yf a man be not fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſober,<note place="margin">Roma. iii.</note> he ſwa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loweth him vp, euen as hel doth a lyuyng man. But if he can not ſo ouercome him, then bryngeth he vnto him welthe and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytie, &amp; promoteth him, dryuing him therby into a deceite that is more greuous and haynouſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any other affection is. That is, that he maketh a man proude, &amp; without feare. This draweth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mynde into the deepe of fleſhlye pleaſures. This maketh the mouth to blaſpheme heuen. For it is written. <hi>They ſtretche forthe their mouthe agaynſt heauen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 73.</note> Thys cauſeth that a man knoweth not God, that he knoweth not hys own infirmitie, that he thinketh not of death and the daie of iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement. This is the waye of all euils. He y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> delighteth to walke
<pb facs="tcp:3894:17"/>
this waye, that is in the way of wealth and eaſe he ſhall come at length into the gates of deathe. This is the waye which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde ſpeaketh of.<note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Brode and wide is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way that leadeth to deſtruction.</hi> Lo, my brother, nowe haſt thou herd for what cauſe the enemye doth ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye to brynge vnto vs ſomtyme proſperitie, ſomtymes aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye. For as he fyndeth the mans mynde affected whiche ſtryueth agaynſt him, euen ſo doeth he w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his euils appoynte his armye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte him. Therfore my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be ſober and take hede and gyue thy ſelfe alwayes to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng, that it may teach the, how thou oughteſt to auoide the ſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of the enemie, and to obtaine euerlaſtynge lyfe. For the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge of holy Scriptures doth make the wandrynge wytte to
<pb facs="tcp:3894:17"/>
ſtande ſtedfaſte, and doeth gyue vnto it the knowledge of God.</p>
            <p>Heareſt thou nowe (my brother) that he getteth the knowledge of God, whiche with an earneſt mynde gyueth diligence to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Scriptures? Therefore, my brother, do not lyghtlye eſteme thy ſoule, but be diligent in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge, and in prayers: that light may be gyuen vnto thy mynde, &amp; thou maieſt be made a perfecte and whole man, wantynge no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng in any poynte. Let other men glory in kepyng the compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye of great men, of Prynces &amp; Kynges. But do thou glorye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Aungels of God, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng vnto God, and vnto the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye Goſte, by the holy Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. For he that ſpeaketh vnto the by them, is the holy Goſte.</p>
            <p>Gyue dylygence therfore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou
<pb facs="tcp:3894:18"/>
contynually watche to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng of the holy ſcriptures, and to prayer. For as often as thou there through kepeſt companye with God, ſo often are thy ſoule, body and ſprite ſanctified &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed. Be ſure therfore of thys, brother, that when thou happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them thou art halowed. Gyue diligence therfore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou often gyue heede vnto them. And though thy handes haue no ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, yet praye in thy mynde. For bleſſed Anne the mother of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phete Samuel,<note place="margin">i. Meg i.</note> dyd praye &amp; her lyppes onely dyd moue: and her prayer entered into the eares of the Lorde of Sobaoth, and the thynge that ſhe aſked was grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted vnto her. Therfore my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, although thy handes be not at leiſure, yet praye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy mind, for God heareth alſo, euen them
<pb facs="tcp:3894:18"/>
that holde theyr peace. And yf thou canſt not reade, be then of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place where thou maieſt heare, and take profite.<note place="margin">Eccleſi. vi.</note> For it is wryten. <hi>And if thou ſeeſt a man of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandyng, get thee ſoone vnto hym, and let thy foote tread vpon the ſteppes of his dores.</hi> But this is meete not onely for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that can not reade, but that can alſo. For there are many whiche do reade, and they knowe not what they reade.</p>
            <p>Wherfore my brother take heed that thou dyſpiſe not the grace that is in the, which is gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the by the gyfte of Chriſt, but take heede, and ſeke howe thou maieſt pleaſe the Lorde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou maieſt get vnto thy ſelf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of his ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes: as it is writen. <hi>Bleſſed are they whiche ſearche for hys teſtimonies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; do ſeke hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their whole herte.</hi> Take heede that the enemy
<pb facs="tcp:3894:19"/>
hyndre the not, that when thou ſhuldeſt read he make the ſlouth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full, and caſt the into ſuche buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes as ſhall withdrawe the, ſayinge: Dyſpatche thys thynge fyrſt, it is but a lytle thynge, and then ſhalte thou reade withoute anye care. For howe often putteth he theſe thinges into thy mynde, that he maye make thee chereful vnto the workes of thy handes? But he doth caſt al ſuch thynges into thy mind to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende that he may withdrawe the fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> readynge, and from thy greater profyte. For the Deuyll when he ſeeth a man dyſpoſed vnto rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, he ſetteth him ſelfe againſt him with theſe or other ſuch like occaſions, ſeakyng if he by anye meanes may let him. But do not thou obey vnto him, but be as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> herte whiche thriſteth &amp; deſireth<note place="margin">Pſal. xli.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:3894:19"/>
to come to the ſpringes of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that is to ſaye, to the holye ſcriptures, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou mayeſt drinke of them, and that they maye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhe thy thirſt, which art burnt with ſo many affeccyons. But drinke of them which are meete, and are profytable for thee. As for example, when God gyueth the this gyfte that thou vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeſt ſome ſayinge, let it not ſlyppe: but thynke vpon it in thy mynde, and write it in thy herte, and ſo ſhalt thou alwayes reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber the ſame. For it is written.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſhall meditate in thy iuſtyfiynges.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119</note> And agayne. <hi>I haue hydden vp thy wordes in my herte, that I ſhould not ſynne agaynſt thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And agayne. <hi>Wherewithall ſhall a yong man cleuſe his waye? euen in kea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge thy word.</hi> Wel beloued thou ſeeſt that by the remembrynge
<pb facs="tcp:3894:20"/>
the worde of God, a man doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende his lyfe. For who is it whiche is myndefull of the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges of God, and doeth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende hys waye? Is he not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togither a caſtaway &amp; a wretch, whiche remembreth nothyng at all, but forgetteth eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges alſo which he knoweth? To him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſuch a one God ſpeketh. <hi>Wherfore doeſt thou preache my lawes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; takeſt my couenaunt in thy mouthe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth that that ſhalbe taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him which he ſemeth to haue.<note place="margin">Mat. xiii. Mark. iiii. Luke. viii</note> But what is that thynge whyche is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to be taken from hym whiche he ſemeth to haue? euen faythe: for he calleth him ſelfe a Chriſtiane,<note place="margin">Titus i.</note> but he denyeth it in deedes, and is worſe then an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fydell. Therfore he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth the holy gooſte to be taken from
<pb facs="tcp:3894:20"/>
him whiche he receyued in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day of his redempcyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whiche he ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to haue: ſo that ſuche a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is lyke a wyne veſſell, which ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth oute by reaſon of a leake, wherthrough the wyne is loſte: whiche thynge they that knowe not, where they ſee the veſſell, thyncke that it is full: but when any wyne ſhoulde be drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of it, then appeareth it vnto all men that it is emptie. In lyke maner alſo ſuch a man when an accompte ſhalbe aſked of him at the daye of iudgement, he ſhalbe found emptie, and then his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes ſhalbe open vnto all men. Of this ſort are they alſo which ſhal ſaye vnto the kynge at that day. <hi>Lord haue we not prophecied,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. vii.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; in thi na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me haue we not done many good dedes?</hi> And when the kynge anſwereth he ſhall ſaye vnto theym.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3894:21"/>Verely I ſay vnto you, I know you not Thou ſeeſt brother that ſuche a one hath nothyng at al. Be thou therfore myndfull of the worde, and directe thy way. Take hede that thou doeſt not ſuffer the bir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des to lyght downe &amp; to eate vp the ſeede of the ſonne of God.<note place="margin">Luke. viii.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For he ſayd, that <hi>the ſeede is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word whiche ye do heare.</hi> Hyde therefore the ſeede in the furrowes of thy hert, that is to ſay, hyde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word in the myddeſt of thy herte, that thou mayeſt brynge forthe vnto God ſome frute in feare. But when thou readeſt, reade dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly and earneſtly, and handle the ſentence weying it aduiſedly: la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour not to reade ouer many lea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues: but if thou chaunce vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny harde thynge, let it not greue the to read ouer that verſe twis or thriſe, tyll thou vnderſtande
<pb facs="tcp:3894:21"/>
the meanynge and pyth of it.</p>
            <p>But when thou prepareſt thy ſelfe to ſytte downe to reade, or elles to heare an other, pray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God fyrſt, ſaying:</p>
            <p>Lord Ieſu Chriſt open mine eyes and the eares of my hearte that they may heare thy wordes and vnderſtande them:<note place="margin">A prayer</note> and that they maye do thy wyll O Lord.<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> For I am a ſtraunger in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, hyde not thy commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dementes from me. But open myne eyes, &amp; I ſhall beholde the maruayles of thy law. For in thee o my God haue I truſted, that thou maieſt gyue lyght vnto my herte.</p>
            <p>Yea my brother I beſech the praye ſo alwayes vnto god that he wyl gyue lyght vnto thy mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyl make ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the the ſtrength of his wordes: For manye haue erred truſtynge to
<pb facs="tcp:3894:22"/>
their owne wytte, and ſayinge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were wyſe,<note place="margin">Roma. i.</note> they became fooles, and dyd not vnderſtande the thynges that were written, and ſo fallyng into blaſphemies did periſhe. If thou therfore in thy readyng, fynde anye thynge that is hard to be vnderſtanded, take heed that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked enemie do not teache the to ſaye within thyne owne ſelfe: it is not ſo as that worde ſpeaketh. For howe ſhoulde it be ſo? and on ſuch like ſorte. But if thou beleue god, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue his wordes alſo: &amp; ſay vnto the Deuyll. Go behynde me ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie:<note place="margin">Mat. xvi.</note> for I knowe thee not. <hi>The wordes of the Lorde are pure wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. xii.</note> 
               <hi>as the ſiluer whiche from the erthe is tried, &amp; purified ſeuen times in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fire.</hi> There is no euel thynge in them nor doubtful, but all thynges in them co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayned are good in their
<pb facs="tcp:3894:22"/>
ſight that are wyſe, and al thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in them are perfecte to them that find knowledge. But I am a fole, &amp; am ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, yet I know that they are writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpiritually. For the Apoſtle ſayeth that the lawe is ſpirituall. And ſo loke thou vp in to Heauen and ſaye. Lorde I haue beleued thy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and ſaye not agaynſt them,<note place="margin">A prayer</note> but I truſt vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes of thy holy ghoſt. Therfore ſaue me thou O Lorde, that I may fynd fauour before thee. For I ſeake no other thynge but onelye that I maye be ſaued O mercyfull: that I maye obtayne thy grace, for thyne is the kyngdome &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye for euer So be it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:3894:23"/>
            <head>¶An Home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye of the Reſurrection of Chriſte, and of the power and frute therof, written in Latyn by Iohn Brenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, and tranſlated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Englyſhe by T.S.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Owe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhal ſpeake of the Reſurrection of our Lord Ieſu Chriſt, I deſyre you that you all wyl herken with ſuche eares and myndes, not as vayne men are wont to gyue to ydle, &amp; now and then alſo to hurtefull, tales, whiche do onely ſeake this, that they maye be delyghted &amp; waſte the tyme, but with ſuche eares and myndes as very godly men
<pb facs="tcp:3894:23"/>
do gyue to hym that entreateth of the moſt highe and chiefe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier of holy relygion, and of oure perpetual ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For if Chriſt had not ryſen agayne, our prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge hadde been in vayne, as Paule ſayeth, oure faythe were in vayne, the teſtimonye of the Apoſtles of the reſurrection of Chriſte were in vayne, the dead ſhulde not ryſe agayne, we ſhuld yet remayne in our ſynnes: all they which are fallen a ſleape in Chriſt were loſte: finally yf that in this lyfe only we had faith in Chriſt we were the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of all men. Wherfore, moſt dere frendes, if euer we dyd care (as there ought to be none other ſo greate a care) to knowe the thynges that Chriſt dyd, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe of our ſaluacion doſt moſt aboue all thynges enforce vs, that we
<pb facs="tcp:3894:24"/>
well do vnderſtande the ryſyng agayne of Chriſt from the dead. We ſhall firſt therfore ſhew that Chriſte verely is riſen from the dead, then what profyte, what glorye, what maieſtye, the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection did bringe to Chriſt him ſelfe. Laſtly what profyte, what health, yea and what happines hath happened vs, euen vnto vs I ſaye, by the reſurrection of Chriſte.<note place="margin">i. Tim. ii.</note> Remember (Paule wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to Timothe) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ieſus Chriſt roſe agayne from deathe. By which admonicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he doth meane, that there oughte nothynge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monges godly men to be more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteamed then the reſurrection of Chriſte. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may here take my begynnynge, not only thoſe argumentes by which Chriſt ſhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wed him ſelf alyue vnto his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples after his reſurrection, do
<pb facs="tcp:3894:24"/>
wytneſſe the ryſynge agayne of Chriſte from the deade, but alſo the prophecies of the prophetes which were before the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt. In the .xv. pſalme he ſaith. Therfore dyd my herte reioyce, and my tong was glad, moreouer my fleſhe alſo ſhal reſt in hope: Becauſe thou wylte not leaue my ſoule in hell, neyther wylte ſuffre thyne holye one, to ſe corrupcion. And in an other Pſalme. The Lorde ſayd to my lorde, ſyt on my ryght hande, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll I make thyn enemyes a fote<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtole vnder thy feete. And that theſe be prophecies of the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Chriſte, Peter wytneſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth in his firſt ſermon which he made vpon witſondaye, as it is written in the ſecond chapter of the Actes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles. To this agreeth Eſaie. Hys ſepulchre
<pb facs="tcp:3894:25"/>
(ſayth he) ſhall be glorious: For it appeareth by the begynnynge of that chapter (which is the .xi.) that Eſaye in that place doeth preache of Chriſt, and Paule ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth the ſame in the .xv. chap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter to the Romayns. And againe Eſay ſayeth in the .liii. chapter.</p>
            <p>After that he hathe offered hys lyfe for ſynne he ſhall ſe long la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge ſeede, and the wyll of the Lorde ſhalbe ruled in his hande. For becauſe that his ſoule hath labored, he ſhall ſee, and be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficed. And that the Prophete in thys place doeth preache of Chriſte thou ſhalte playnely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue, by the .viii. chapter of the Actes of the Apoſtles. But what neade any more? Wherſoeuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophetes do preach of the euer laſtynge kyngdome of Chriſte, there alſo do they preache of the
<pb facs="tcp:3894:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
reſurrectio of Chriſt. For Chriſt coulde not haue obtayned an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtyng kyngdom, excepte he had ryſen from death into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glo glory of his father. Now, Chriſt alſo himſelfe did ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and much before his deathe, prophecye of his reſurrection from death.</p>
            <p>Deſtroye (ſayth he) this temple, and in three dayes wyll I rayſe it vp agayne. And againe: as Io<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nas was in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> belly of the Whale three dayes, and thre nightes, ſo ſhal the ſonne of manne be in the herte of the earth, three dayes, &amp; three nightes. And agayne. The Sonne of man muſt ſuffre many thinges, &amp; be reproued of the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, &amp; chiefe prieſtes, &amp; ſcribes, and be ſlayne, and the thyrde day ryſe agayne. Agayne: It is writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten, I ſhall ſmyte the ſhepeherd, and the ſhepe of the Rocke ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be
<pb facs="tcp:3894:26"/>
that I am ryſen, I wyll go into Galile before you. But what do I? The thinges whiche Chriſte before his death preached of his reſurrection, be muche more kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen by the hiſtories of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels then that the ſame nede in this place with many wordes to be repeted. But theſe are prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyes of the reſurrection, before that it was done. But after that it was done, there was no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or occaſion let paſſe, in which Chriſt did not playnly witneſſe, that he was in deede ryſen from the deade. Theſe we ſhall nowe paſſe ouer, for bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in our en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>treating of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hiſtorie of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, they are handeled at large, ſauing that we wyll adde thys herunto, that the Apoſtles were chiefelye ordeyned for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
<pb facs="tcp:3894:26"/>
that they ſhoulde wytneſſe the reſurrection of Chriſt. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore (ſaieth Peter) of theſe men whiche haue companyed wyth vs all the tyme that the Lorde Ieſu hadde his conuerſation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge vs,<note place="margin">Actes. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> begynning at the bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme of Iohn, vnto that ſame daye that he was taken vp from vs, muſt one be ordeyned to bee a wytnes wyth vs of hys reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. And agayne.<note place="margin">Actum. x.</note> Hym God rayſed vp the thirde day and ſhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wed him openly, not vnto all the people, but vnto vs wytneſſes, choſen before of God for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame entent, whiche dyd eate &amp; drinke with hym, after that he roſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death. Briefly as the prophecies of the prophetes concernyng the reſurrection of Chriſte, are the moſte true ſothe ſayinges of the holy ghoſte, ſo is there nothynge
<pb facs="tcp:3894:27"/>
more certayne, then that Chriſte veryly is riſen from the dead, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in dede. Wherof we ſhall ſpeake more herafter. Nowe let vs ſee what he hathe gotten by his Reſurrection. Chriſt truly is not riſen from death in ſuch ſort as that dead man whiche by the touchynge of the carkais of the prophet Eliſeus reuyued,<note place="margin">4. Reg xiii</note> to dye agayn,<note place="margin">Luke. vii Iohn. xi.</note> nether yet as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſon of the wydowe, neither as Lazarus y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> had lien .iiii.<note place="margin">Actes. ix.</note> dayes in his graue, neither as Dorcas in Ioppa, were called agayne to lyfe. For theſe verelye were rayſed from deth, but i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to this corporal life to die agayne. But Chriſt ryſen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death (as Paule ſayeth) dieth no more,<note place="margin">Actes. xiii</note> death hath no more power ouer him. And agayne: He raiſed hym vp from deth now no more to returne to corruption. And
<pb facs="tcp:3894:27"/>
that I maye comprehende all in one worde, Chriſte by his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection entered into his glorye.</p>
            <p>For he ſayth in Luke.<note place="margin">Luk. xxiiii.</note> Oughte not Chriſt to haue ſuffered theſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges and to enter into his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye. Here therfore we muſt trye out what the glory of Chriſt is.<note place="margin">The glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of Chriſte.</note> Firſt truely the glory of Chriſte is, that he is the Sonne of God. In to this glory therfore he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by his reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is, he proued by his reſurrection y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was in deede the Sonne of god.<note place="margin">Roma. i.</note> He is declared (ſaith Paul) to be the ſonne of god w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> power, after the ſpirit, that ſanctifieth, ſence the time that Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde roſe agayne frome death. And this glory is greater then that it can worthyly be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with wordes. Wherfore we ſhall touche the other partes
<pb facs="tcp:3894:28"/>
of his glory, and maieſtye. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condlye the glorye of Chriſte is that he is, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame bleſſednes, maieſty, and almightie power w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God his father. Wherfore into this glorye alſo he entred in by his reſurrection. Sit (ſaieth the father) on my right hande, vntill I make thyne enemyes thy fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtole. Furthermore, the glorye of Chriſte is that all thynges are ſubiecte vnto him, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is Lorde of heauen and earth, and Iudge of the lyuynge and of the deade. This maieſtye Chriſte receyued by his reſurrection.<note place="margin">Philip, ii,</note> God hath ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>alted him (ſayth Paule) on hye, and gyuen him a name which is aboue all names, that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Ieſus euery one ſhuld bowe, bothe of thinges in heauen, and thynges in earthe, and thynges vnder the earthe. And agayne.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3894:28"/>Chriſt therfore dyed and roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, &amp; reuiued,<note place="margin">Rom xiiii,</note> that he myght be Lorde ouer dead and quicke.<note place="margin">Actes. xvii.</note> And agayne. He hath appoynted a daye in the which he wil iudge the worlde by that man by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath appoynted, and hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered faith vnto all men, after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had rayſed hym from death. But who canne eyther by thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng conceiue, ether els by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, I ſaye not expreſſe, but no more but ſomwhat touche al the partes of that glorye &amp; maieſtie, whiche Chriſt by his reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did receyue? Wherfore lettynge paſſe this parte of the ſermon, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendyng it rather vnto faith, then ſhewyng it vnto mans rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, we ſhall come to thys y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we put forthe in the thred place, and whiche is moſt of all to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered of vs and with greate ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye
<pb facs="tcp:3894:29"/>
to be ſearched for, that is to ſaye, what profyte, what healthe or happynes the reſurrection of Chriſt hath brought vnto vs me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ite by Chriſtes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eath.</note> And for bycauſe that nowe we are come to ſpeake of the chiefe poynte of relygion, yea and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matier of our whole ſaluacyon, we wyll not brynge forth mans dreames, but wyl gather places of the holy ſcripture, by whyche we ſhal ſhewe that the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt is our very and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtyng ſaluacyon. And fyrſte of the profyt of the reſurrection of Chriſt there is nothyng in the ſcriptures more ſhorte, &amp; cleare, then that Paule writethe to the Romaynes,<note place="margin">Rom iiii,</note> ſaying: He was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered for our ſinnes, and was rayſed agayne for oure iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. For as the death of Chriſte hathe pourged oure ſynnes, and
<pb facs="tcp:3894:29"/>
hath brought to paſſe, that oure ſynnes are forgyuen vs of God for Chriſtes ſake, ſo the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Chriſte, hath brought vnto vs ryghteouſnes, and hath brought to paſſe that as manye as beleue in Chriſt, may be eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med before God euen righteous for Chriſtes ſake. They truly are called bleſſed, whoſe iniquitie is forgyuen, and whoſe ſynnes are couered, but oure ſynnes are not couered but with true and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte righteouſnes. And we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuche as partaineth vnto our nature, are ſo far from perfecte rightwiſnes, as the heuen is fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth. For albeit that manye haue a cyuile honeſty and righte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſnes, yet do they want in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the true &amp; perfect righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes. Therfore Chriſte roſe agayne from death to this ende,
<pb facs="tcp:3894:30"/>
that as by his death he hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned, that God the father for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyueth vs our ſynnes, and is be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>come fauourable vnto vs, ſo by his reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhuld obtaine, that God ſhuld impute vnto vs all the righteouſnes of Chriſt, &amp; that he ſhoulde not otherwyſe iudge of vs, then as if we by our workes had perfectly fulfylled all righteouſneſſe. Whiche ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not (ſayth he) his own ſonne,<note place="margin">Rom. viii.</note> but gaue him for vs all, howe can it be, that with him he ſhuld not giue vs al thinges alſo? For vnto Chriſte belongeth true and perfecte ryghtwiſnes. Seynge therfore that Chriſt is gyuen vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to death for vs, and is gyuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs by hys Reſurrection, it is playne alſo that by his reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion his rightwiſnes is ſo gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs that we may glory of it
<pb facs="tcp:3894:30"/>
as of our owne, and we may ſet it not ſo muche againſt the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynges of our ſynnes, as againſt the gates of hell. Peter ſayeth, that baptiſme ſaueth vs,<note place="margin">i. Peter. iii</note> not the puttynge away of the fylthe of the fleſhe, but the promyſe or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenaunte of a good conſcyence towardes God, by the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Ieſus Chriſt. For as for vs, whether we conſider our ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes or the ryghtwyſnes of oure fleſhe, we haue an euil co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcyence, and we do knowe that we are gyltye of euerlaſtyng damnacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: For oure ſynnes verelye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do dyrectlye fyghte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the wyl and law of God: For our ryghtwyſneſſe alſo, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our rightwiſnes is bothe imperfect &amp; vnpure. But a good conſcyence (ſayethe Peter) is wroughte in vs, by the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:3894:31"/>
of Chriſte. Howe? bycauſe God knytteth himſelfe vnto vs by a couenaunt, and ſtricketh vp a bargayne in maner wyth hys hand with vs, by the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hys Sonne, that he wyll for Chriſte his ſonnes ſake, knowe and iudge vs perfectlye righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and make vs ſaued. If the conſcyence do know theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges by faith, what can be better then it? what more quiet, &amp; euen in the myddes of death, yea in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> horryble iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, what more ſecure? Herto belongeth it that Peter alſo in an other place ſayth.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Peter. i</note> Bleſſed be God, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to his abundant mercy, begat vs agayne vnto a lyuelye hope. By what? it foloweth: by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, that Ieſus Chriſte roſe agayne from deathe. But what is that lyuely hope, into the whiche the
<pb facs="tcp:3894:31"/>
reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt hath begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vs agayne? Forſothe this it is: that God hath giuen vnto vs by the reſurrection of Chriſte, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true, whole, and perfecte ryght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſnes, whiche Chriſt the ſonne of God, hath, that by it we ſhuld obtayne an immortall, vndefy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and an enheritaunce that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth not, euen in heuen. What could therfore happen vnto vs more profitable, yea or els more neceſſarye then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſurrection of Chriſt?<note place="margin">i. Cor. xv.</note> And true it is that Paul ſaith. If Chriſt be not ryſen, you are yet in your ſinnes. But now he is ryſen agayne: We are not onely therfore delyuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſynnes as many of vs as byleue in him, but alſo the ſame ryght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſnes whiche he hathe is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted alſo vnto vs, perfecte and on euery ſide ſufficiently perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.
<pb facs="tcp:3894:32"/>
Furthermore the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſte hath brought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs not only oure victory ouer afflyctions, and death, but alſo oure owne reſurrection fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deth into lyfe, and euerlaſtynge bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe. Chriſt (ſayth Paule) is riſen from the dead and become the fyrſt fruites of theim y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſlepe. For by a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> came death, and by a man came the reſurrection of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deade. For as by Adam al do die, euen ſo by Chriſte ſhall all be made alyue. For, to the ende that we maye rightly vnderſtand the benefite of Chriſte, we muſt not conſyder and beholde Chriſt by his outwarde body only, that is to ſay, by one parte of hys or one member only, but by his whole and perfecte ſpiritual body. For ſo doth Paule teache y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſte is to be conſidered of vs, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he
<pb facs="tcp:3894:32"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to the Epheſias, ſayi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge: He hath made hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the heade of the congrega<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon, whiche is his body.<note place="margin">Epheſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the whole bodye of man is made of the heade and manye members, ſo whole Chriſte is made (foraſmuche as nowe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth for our purpoſe) of his own perſon as the heade, and of all them that beleue in him as of di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſe membres. But nowe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as it is playne, that Chriſte the heade is riſen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead, how coulde it be, that he ſhoulde not drawe alſo with him ſelfe al his membres from death, vnto lyfe, and reſurrection? Shuld y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head ryſe, and leaue behynde hym, the hande or the fote, yea or ſo much as the lytle fynger? Chriſt (thou wylt ſay) dyd ryſe alone, bicauſe no man aſcended into heauen,
<pb facs="tcp:3894:33"/>
but he whiche deſcended. Verye wel, he roſe alone: but this muſt be added, that he alſo dyd ryſe whole. Whole Chriſt is, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head, with his members. Whither ſo euer therfore the heade is come, euen thither alſo are the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres comen. And who are the true me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of Chriſte, but they that beleue i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him? Do you not know, ſayth Paule, that youre bodyes are the membres of Chriſt? And agayne: We are members of the ſame body, of hys fleſſhe, and of his bones. It is therfore many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that as manye as beleue in Chriſte, are riſen togither wyth Chriſte.<note place="margin">Epheſ. li.</note> Whereof Paule ſaieth: When we were dead by ſynnes, he quickned vs togyther wyth Chriſte (by grace are ye ſaued) &amp; raiſed vs vp together with him, and made vs to ſyt together w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3894:33"/>
him amonge them of heauen, in Chriſte Ieſu. And agayn:<note place="margin">Coloſ. ii.</note> Ye are buried with him throughe bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, in whome ye are ryſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne throughe faythe, that is wroughte by the operacyon of God, whiche rayſed hym frome deathe. And ye when ye were dead through ſinne, and through the vncircumciſion of your fleſh, hath he quickened with him, and hath forgiuen vs all our treſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. For as Chriſte hath drawne al them that beleue in him togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him ſelfe into his deth and burial: We are buried (ſaith Paule) together wyth hym by baptiſme for to dye:<note place="margin">Rom. v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hath he drawen with himſelfe them into his reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo that as many as are deade &amp; buryed together with Chriſt, they haue alſo ryſen agayne with Chriſte: Whether we lyue (ſayeth he) or<note place="margin">Rom. xiiij</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:3894:34"/>
we dye, we are the Lordes. For Chriſte therfore died and roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, that he myght be Lorde ouer the deade and quicke. But thou wylte ſaye howe haue we ryſen againe with Chriſt, which do yet notwithſtandynge lyue in this mortal body, and nedes we muſt dye? We ſayde afore, that nowe we are occupied in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt highe matier of our ſaluacion.</p>
            <p>Wherfore we muſte bring forth not mans dreames, but the wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſynges of God. Let vs heare therfore Chriſtes owne ſermon of this matter.<note place="margin">Iohn. iii.</note> As Moſes (ſaith he) lyfted vp the ſerpente in the wyldernes, euen ſo muſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of man be lyfte vp, that who ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer beleueth in him, periſhe not, but haue euerlaſtynge lyfe. And Paul:<note place="margin">Roma. x,</note> Yf thou knowledge with thy mouth that Ieſus is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, and doſt beleue in thy herte, that
<pb facs="tcp:3894:34"/>
God rayſed hym vp fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhalte be ſaued. For notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge that after the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt, we are yet mortall me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in earthe, and ſubiecte to all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſyties, yet by faythe, I ſaye, by faith in Chriſt we ar ſo made partakers of his reſurrection,<note place="margin">We ſhall riſe agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> firſt vnto vs truely doth belong the ryght of ryſynge from death vnto euerlaſtyng bleſſednes in the laſt daye. For fayth doeth fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten vs, and as I myght ſo ſaye doth incorporate vs to Chriſte. Sens therfore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſte in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are incorporate is riſen, it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be, that we ſhoulde not ryſe with him. For as touchynge it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as yet we do die, and our bodies do rotte in the earthe, yea or be brent with fire, ſhoulde thys be any let to our reſurrection? For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſothe, God, whiche when as yet there was nothyng, could make
<pb facs="tcp:3894:35"/>
thys ſo greate a woorke of thys worlde, coulde he not alſo fynde againe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body which was made before, yea though it wer turned into duſt, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, or the ſea, &amp; cal it agayne vnto life? God doth cal thoſe thynges which are not, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they maye bee,<note place="margin">Iohn. xii.</note> &amp; can he not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> call againe thoſe thynges which ſeme to haue peryſſhed? Hathe he not ſet furth vnto vs in euery lytle grayne the ymage of our re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Except y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wheat corne (ſaieth Chriſt) fal into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ground and dye, it bringeth forthe no fruit. And Paule ſayeth. Thou foole,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. xv.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſoweſt, is not quickened, excepte it dye. And what ſoweſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi>? Thou ſoweſt not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body that ſhalbe, but bare corne, as of wheate, or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but god gyueth it a body at his pleaſure, to euery ſeade his own body. Which of vs can ſee i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:3894:35"/>
a cornell of a Peare ſo greate a boughe of a tre, as groweth out of it, beyng layed in the ground? Who ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſee in a grain of corne ſo great a ſtalke &amp; an eare as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers do reape? Man doth not ſe, but God ſeith, which alſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth theſe. And ſhuld he rayſe vp a dead grayne or ſeade, &amp; not a man? For not onlye that he can, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wil alſo raiſe vs from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deade, he hath not only teſtified by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſurrection of Chriſte his Sonne, but alſo by manye other argumentes, promyſes, &amp; mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, which wer long now to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pete. The reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead truly is by ſcriptures ſo certaine &amp; ſure, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly reherſed in the common confeſſion of our fayth. Wherfore there is nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g more ſurely to be holden, then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> throughe Chriſte the righte and glorye of the Reſurrection from
<pb facs="tcp:3894:36"/>
the deade vnto euerlaſtynge bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſedneſſe belongeth euen vnto vs. Furthermore when we beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we through Chriſte ſhall ryſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, this faith canne not be y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in vs, but euen nowe, whiles yet we are in this mortal body it doth thinke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For as in the yong plantes it do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth furthwith appere what the fruites wylbe, and in the wittes of chyldren it is anone ſhewed furth what thinge is to be loked for of them, euen ſo in the godly the reſurrection that is to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me doeth begynne to bringe forthe his frute whiles that we do yet lyue in the earth. Moſes was appoynted of god to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer and law gyuer to Iſrael. But he dyd not onelye then execute this offyce, when he brought the people oute of Egypte, but the appoyntment of this office that
<pb facs="tcp:3894:36"/>
he ſhulde take in hande beganne euen then alſo to worke in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, when as yet he being a child (if we wyl beleue Ioſephus) he threwe downe the crowne roiall of the kyng of Egipt, trode it vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der his feete: When as he ſlewe the Egipcian that dyd wrong to the Iſraelite, when he laboured to agree the Iſraelites whiche ſtroue together, and when he did deliuer the daughters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſt of Madian from the wrong of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhepeherdes. Theſe trulye were the begi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ninges of his office y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhoulde haue. Dauid was choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kinge of Iſraell. But this electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was not idle in Dauid vntill that time that after the death of Saule he was openly called to be kinge of the people. But Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid euen then began to take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him lyke a kynge, when as in the kepynge of his ſhepe he ſlewe a
<pb facs="tcp:3894:37"/>
Beare and a Lyon, and when w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a bolde ſtomacke he ſet vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liathe and ſlewe him. So y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith of the reſurrection ſhal not onely practiſe his power in rayſynge oure bodyes vnto euerlaſtynge lyfe in the laſt day: but yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true fayth be in vs, euen in this lyfe alſo doth it ſhew forth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth that it hath: And firſt it holdeth vs vp in al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aduerſities of this lyfe, yea euen in the myddes of death. For if we ſhal ryſe agayn into euerlaſtynge lyfe, the which thing we know by faith that we ſhall do, what diſaduauntage (I praye you) what euill happe can aduerſities yea or deathe it ſelf, bringe vnto vs? I praye the, if a man ſhoulde put of frome the a fylthy garmente, to put on vpon the and clothe the with a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aparel, woldeſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> cal y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> takinge of the fylthy apparel from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduantage,
<pb facs="tcp:3894:37"/>
or euel lucke, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhouldeſt not y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> call it great profit. To ſuffer aduerſity i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this world &amp; at length to dye, ſurlye they be nothing els, then a put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting away of anold &amp; filthy gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou maieſt take vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> a moſt gorgius garment. We do know (ſaith Paul) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if our earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mancio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thys dwelling wer deſtroyed,<note place="margin">ii. Cor. v.</note> we haue a building of god, an habitacion not made w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> handes, but eternall in heauen. For therfore ſigh we, deſiringe to be clothed with our manſyon which is fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wherefore, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by fayth we do thinke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deth thorow Chriſt, it can not be but that we ſhal get y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vyctory, not only ouer al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of this world, but alſo of death &amp; hel. Moreouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame faith of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth begin or exerciſe in vs the newe
<pb facs="tcp:3894:38"/>
lyfe,<note place="margin">A newe lyfe.</note> worthye the Reſurrection, that forſakinge all vngodlynes and vnrightuouſnes we may fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe all kyndes of heauenlye vertues. For verylye excepte the newnes of lyfe dothe folow the faythe of the reſurreccion, it is a playne argument that the fayth is deade. And what is there that ſhould be a lyue in a manne when as hys faythe lyueth not, whiche is the lyfe of the Iuſte manne. For the Iuſte (ſaieth he) lyueth by faythe. Wherefore in this aboue all thinges muſte we moſt chiefly labour, that we do ſhew forth our true faith of the reſurrection by good woorkes, and beinge yet in the earthe we maye lyue an heuenly lyfe. For true rightuouſnes is broughte and gyuen vnto vs by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Chriſt in ſuch ſort, that god doth iudge vs for Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes
<pb facs="tcp:3894:38"/>
ſake Iuſt and holy in dede. Howe then could this ſtand to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, that we deſpyſinge and defilynge that rightuouſnes of Chriſte, ſhoulde lyue in vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſnes? The reſurrection of Chriſte hathe called vs backe from deathe, to lyfe, and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge bleſſednes. What nowe is more vile, yea what is more pernicious, then forſaking life, to make himſelfe bonde againe to deathe, and euerlaſtyng miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyefe. He whoſoeuer it bee that foloweth ſynne dothe gyue himſelfe to deathe, and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinge deſtruction. For the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde (ſaythe he) of ſynne is deathe.<note place="margin">Rom. vi.</note> In the policy of Moſes it was moſte ſtraitly commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that no manne contynuinge the daies of the feaſt of the paſſe ouer ſhould eat leauened bread. He that eateth (ſaythe he) leaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned<note place="margin">Exod x. ii.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:3894:39"/>
breade, his lyfe ſhall peryſhe out of the congregacion of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, aſwell of ſtraungers as of dwellers in the lande. This law precheth vnto vs, that after that Chriſt who is oure paſſe ouer is riſen from deathe, it is lawfull for no man to haue felowſhippe either with vncleane and vngod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly menne, eyther elles to leade an vncleane lyfe, or a lyfe leaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with ſinnes.<note place="margin">i. Cor. v.</note> Purge ye ſaith Paule the olde leauen, that ye maye be new doughe, as ye are vnleauened for Chriſte our paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cale lambe is offered vp for vs. Therfore let vs kepe holye daye not with old leaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neither with the leue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of maliouſnes &amp; wicked<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, but with the ſwete breade of purenes and trueth. For they that do ſtil go forwarde in their wickednes and Iniquitie thoſe men (horrible it is to ſay) do for
<pb facs="tcp:3894:39"/>
aſmuch as in them lyeth, crucify Chriſt againe, and do deny that he is ryſen from deathe. For the reſurreccion of Chriſte is denied not only with mouthe of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries of oure relygion, but alſo of the vngodlye by their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and workes whiche do lyue amongeſt vs are called chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. For wher as Chriſt by his deathe toke awaye ſynne and by his reſurrection brought againe rightuouſnes, nowe from hence forthe to ſynne and to deſpyſe ryghteouſnes what els is it, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to cal Chriſt againe vnto death, and euen to fyght againſte hys reſurrection? And beholde here the curſed wickednes of thoſe menne whyche do yet folow the luſtes of ſynne. Chriſte truely by his reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brought to paſſe that we ſhoulde be choſen to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children of God, &amp; the enheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours
<pb facs="tcp:3894:40"/>
of all the heauenly goods. But oure ſynnes do cauſe that we become the chyldren of the deuell and the enherytours of euerlaſting fyre. What is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore more horrible, what more curſed, then to rage in ſuch a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of ſynne, that thou doeſt not only vtterlye caſt awaye the choſing wherwith God choſeth the, but alſo thou gyueſt ouer thy ſelfe into the houſhold of the deuill, that thou mayſt with hys Angels peryſhe euerlaſtinglye? For after that Chriſte is riſen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deathe and we be engrafted into his death, we are no longer oure owne men, but his, whiche by hys deathe and reſurrection hath delyuered vs from deathe into lyfe. Therfore we muſte o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey Chriſte, and not ſynne. We are buryed (ſaythe paule) with him by baptyſme for to die,<note place="margin">Roma. vi.</note> that
<pb facs="tcp:3894:40"/>
lykewyſe as Chryſt was raiſed from deathe by the glory of the father, euen ſo we alſo ſhoulde walke in a new lyf: And againe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For as towchinge that he died, he died concernynge ſinne ons, and as touching that he lyueth, he lyueth vnto God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lykewyſe Imagin ye alſo, that ye are deade concernynge ſynne: but are alyue vnto god thorow Chriſt Ieſu our Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">ii. Cor. v.</note> 
               <hi>And againe. If one be deade for al, then all were deade, and he died for vs all, that they whiche lyue, ſhould not henſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forthe lyue vnto them ſelues, but vnto hym whiche died for them, and roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne.</hi> And in an other place.<note place="margin">Coloſ. iii.</note> 
               <hi>Yf ye be then riſen agayne with Chriſte, ſeke thoſe thynges whiche are aboue where Chriſt ſitteth on the right hand of god. Set youre affection on thynges that are aboue, and not on thinges whiche are on the earthe.</hi> And what are thoſe thinges on earthe whiche are to be auoyded, and thynges that are aboue to be ſought for. <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify (ſaith he) your earthly me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, vncleanes, vnnatural luſt, euel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cupiſcence, &amp; couetouſnes, wrath, fer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſenes,
<pb facs="tcp:3894:41"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, curſed ſpeaking <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thy ſpeaki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, &amp; put on te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der mercy, kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, humblenes of minde, meknes, ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> &amp; what ſo euer other godlye vertue ther is. For if we do theſe thinges we ſhal not only co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe in wordes &amp; comon ſayinges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt in his owne parſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is riſen againe, but alſo we ſhal teſtify y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he alſo is riſen againe in vs, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he liueth in vs, yea &amp; that al the righte of Chriſtes reſurrection doth belong vnto vs, ſo that we may not onli ouer cum afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; death in this worlde, but that we may alſo get euerlaſting bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſednes in the worlde to comme, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſurrection of Ieſu Chriſt oure Lord, which is together w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father &amp; the holy goſt god to be praiſed for euer &amp; euer So be it.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London, in S. Iohns ſtrete by Nicolas Hyll, for Iohn Shefelde, dwelling in Pauls church yarde.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3894:41"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
